Guide to the John Gladstone Papers WAG.146
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Gladstone Papers
1934-2002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gladstone, John, 1917-
Hernandez, Ideal
Zieger, Robert H.
WAG.146
8 Linear Feet in 14 manuscript boxes and one flat box.
John Gladstone was a member of the National Maritime Union (NMU) and the Communist Party until 1949, when he was expelled from both organizations. He later became a publisher and editor at Engineer's Press, as well as an art historian. The John Gladstone Papers dated 1934-2002, documents NMU and Gladstone's involvement with the organization, maritime labor history more generally, and Gladstone's research and writings on art, literature, history, and politics. The collection includes correspondence, articles and clippings, research notes, manuscripts, publications, photographs, and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by John Gladstone in 2001. The accession number associated with this gift is 2008.030.
Additional materials were donated by Ideal Hernandez in 2006 and 2009. The accession number associated with this gift is 2009.067.
One folder of correspondence was possibly donated by Robert H. Zieger in 2009. The accession number associated with this material is 2009.020.
Arrangement
This collection retains its original order and was minimally physically rearranged. This collection has been intellectually arranged into the following series based on subject matter: Series I. National Maritime Union; Series II. Art, History, and Politics.
Biographical Note
John Gladstone (1917-) was a member of the National Maritime Union and the Communist Party until 1949, when he was expelled from both organizations. He later became a publisher and editor at Engineer's Press, as well as an artist, and art historian. John Gladstone has worked in the refrigeration industry since 1938 and is a life member of the American Society of Heating, Refrigerating and Air-Conditioning Engineers. Gladstone has written 22 books, many of which are estimating guides and handbooks for contractors. Gladstone served briefly on the board of the New York based Maritime Workers Historical Association, an organization formed in part by former NMU members in 1979.
Scope and Content Note
The John Gladstone Papers dated 1934-2002, documents the National Maritime Union and Gladstone's involvement with the organization, and maritime labor history more generally. The collection also contains Gladstone's research and writings on art, literature, history, and politics. The collection includes correspondence, articles and clippings, research notes, manuscripts, publications, photographs, and ephemera.
Industrial technicians -- Labor unions -- United States.; Merchant mariners -- Labor unions -- United States.; Labor unions -- United States -- History; Art historians -- United States.; World politics -- 20th century.; Labor -- History; Marxism -- History.; Socialism -- History.; Politics and literature.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts; National Maritime Union of America; Gladstone, John, 1917-; Hernandez, Ideal; Zieger, Robert H.
- Series I. National Maritime Union
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials related to National Maritime Association (NMU) and maritime labor history more generally. The bulk of the series consists of correspondence between Gladstone and the Maritime Workers Historical Association, including the editors of the organization's publication HAWSEPIPE. There is also correspondence between Gladstone and researchers focused on the history of the National Maritime Union and maritime labor. The publications include the proceedings of several NMU national conventions. The small number of ephemera includes NMU membership cards and books, shore passes, leaflets, handbills, and other printed materials. The small grouping of photographs within this series mostly depict maritime workers circa 1940's.
  - Correspondence, 1943-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-10, Box 2, Folder 1-8, Box 4, Folder 1, Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Articles, clippings, and other printed materials, 1944-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Publications, 1834-1980 (Box 6)
  - Ephemera, 1934-1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 1, Box 14, Folder 4-6)
  - Photographs, circa 1930-1950, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 2, Box 3)
- Series II. Art, History, and Politics
  This series contains Gladstone's papers related to art, history, and politics. The bulk of the series consists of articles, clippings, and research notes on art history. This series also contains several of Gladstone's manuscripts on art history, politics, and the environment, as well as a small number of published technical works. Among the subjects of Gladstone's art-related research and manuscripts are painters Pablo Picasso, Thomas Eakins, and Thomas Anshutz. Much of Gladstone's correspondence relates to art history, literature, labor, Marxism and other leftist politics. The correspondence also includes letters to the editors of various publications concerning domestic and international affairs and policy.
  - Correspondence, 1937-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3, Box 2, Folder 10, Box 4, Folder 2 and 9, Box 10, Folder 3, Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and published works, 1969-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Box 4, Folder 3-4, 6-8, Box 5, Box 7, Folder 3-7, Box 8, Box 9, Folder 1-2, Box 13, Folder 3 and 6)
  - Articles, clippings, and other printed materials, 1935-1996, undated (Box 3, Box 4, Folder 5, Box 9, Folder 3-4, 6-7, Box 10, Folder 1-2, 4-6, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Folder 1-2, 4-5, 7-11, Box 14, Folder 1 and 3)